FANSA KONE

University of Montreal (UdeM) Department of Economics 3150 Jean Brillant Street, C-6070-10 Montreal (Quebec, Canada), H3C 3J7

SUMMARY

I'm a Ph.D. candidate in Economics with a quantitative background in Statistics. I have 6 years of work experience in Cote d'Ivoire and Canada. I'm also a continuous learner with a passion for Macroeconomics, International trade, public finance, and Applied econometrics (quantitative analysis). Besides my technical strengths, I have excellent leadership and communication skills.

EDUCATION

University of Montreal, CIREQ

2019-August 2024

Citizenship: Ivorian

Phone: $+1\ 514\ 561\ 3741$

Email: fansakone@gmail.com

PhD candidate in Economics, Canada

Ecole Nationale Supérieure de Statistiques et d'Economie Appliquée (ENSEA) 2016-2019 MSc in Statistics and Economics (ISE) 2016-2019, Côte d'Ivoire Certified in impact evaluation, Tany Vao and ENSEA, 2019

Institut National Polytechnique Félix Houphouet Boigny

2014-2016

Mathematics and commercial studies, Intensive two-years BSc program 2014-2016, Côte d'Ivoire

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2018-PRESENT

World Bank consultant

December 2022-June 2023

Poverty and Equity Global Practice, World Bank

Effect of Russia's Invasion of Ukraine on Households living conditions in Guinea

E-CEQ: contribution to the analysis of the effect of fiscal policy on genders inequality in Guinea Ex-ante Cost Benefit Analysis and Impact of Togo's cash transfer program on Poverty

Independent consultant

2018-2019

Estimated a Panel-VAR to analyze monetary policy transmission channels in West African Economic and Monetary Union (WAEMU) countries, for a professional, 2018-2019

Participated in the design of survey instruments, data collection, and data processing for household living conditions in Toumodi (Côte d'Ivoire), ENSEA 2018

Teaching (UdeM) 2021-present

Initiation to economics; Fall 2023, Fall 2021

Economics data analysis; Winter 2023 (Online, undergraduate level)

Teaching assistant (UdeM)

2020-present

Advanced macroeconomics; Winter 2022 and 2023 (Ph.D. level) for professor Guillaume Sublet Special topics in money and banking; Fall 2022, 2023 (graduate level) for professor René Garcia Principles of economics; Winter, Summer, Fall 2022 (Online, undergraduate)

Economics data analysis; Fall 2021 (Online, undergraduate)

Introduction to macroeconomics; Fall 2020, Winter 2021

North American economics; Winter 2021, for professor Vasia Panousi

International Finance; Fall 2020, for professor Emanuela Cardia

International trade; Fall 2020, for professor Abraham HOLLANDER

RESEARCH

Research interest

Public finance, International Trade, Monetary Policy and Applied Econometrics

Research in progress

2021-present

Balanced Budget Rule and Economic Growth

WAEMU facing AfCFTA: implications for trade and monetary policies, with Régis Kouassi

Trade, Shocks Transmission, and Monetary Policy in a Regional Trade Agreement, with Régis Kouassi

Presentations 2019-present

Canadian Economic Association, Winnipeg, June 2023

Société Canadienne de Science économique, Québec city, May 2023

18th CIREQ Ph.D. students conference, Montreal, May 2023

Quebec Social Sciences Ph.D. presentations group, Montreal-online, (September 2021, February and October 2022, April 2023)

International Conference of Statistics and Applied Economics (CISEA), July 2019, ENSEA, Abidjan

Before PhD research 2018-2019

Dynamic mean-variance portfolio for the regional stock exchange (BRVM), with Arsène Brou, ENSEA 2019, supervised by Nathaniel Gbenro

Applied quantile regression to examine the determinants of maize yield using household survey in Cote d'Ivoire, Internship at ENSEA 2018, supervised by Jean Mark Kouadio

AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Fonds de Recherche du Québec Science et Culture (FRQSC) fellowships, ranked 2nd, 2022-

Ph.D. fellowships, Department of Economics, UdeM 2019-

Canadian Economics Association students travel grant, Winnipeg, June 2023

Financial assistance from CIREQ (62th SCSE conference), Quebec, May 2023

Tuition-fee Waiver Scholarship of Graduate Studies, University of Montreal, Canada, 2019-2021

Excellence Scolarship, Government of Côte d'Ivoire, high school and university scolarship (2011-2019)

Winner Public Forum Debate (with a team), ENSEA (2019)

Awards "meilleure plume", Writing competition, ENSEA (2017)

Awards of the best scientist at high school level, received from the minister of education at Journée National du Mérite et de l'Excellence (JNMEX), Côte d'Ivoire, 2015

Awards of the best student of high school level at Lycée Mixte I de Yamoussoukro, Côte d'Ivoire, 2014

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Stata, Python, Matlab, Latex (basic knowledge in R. Eviews, SPSS)

Microsoft Excel, Powerpoint, Word

VOLUNTEERING ACTIVITIES

Economics PhD student's representative

Fall 2021-

Defending and representing Ph.D. students in economics' interests at UdeM, Canada

Passerelle and passerelle +

Fall 2020, Winter 2021

Helped new students integrate Université de Montréal in the context of the pandemic, Canada

Université de Montréal ambassador

Fall 2019, Winter 2020

Division des Ingénieurs Statisticiens Economistes

2018-2019

President of "commission recherche emploi" aiming to facilitate students integration to the labor market

Organising activities to help students at ENSEA improve their English skills, Côte d'Ivoire

LANGUAGE AND OTHER INTERESTS

French (native), English (fluent), soccer, reading, writing, badmington

ABSTRACT OF SOME SELECTED WORK IN PROGRESS

Balanced Budget Rule and Economic Growth

Fiscal rules, specifically Balanced Budget Rules (BBR), are gaining widespread acceptance and usage. Yet, the primary economic objection to BBRs is that they overly restrict fiscal policy by preventing tax smoothing and impeding stable growth. This paper studies the impact of a BBR over the business cycle on economic growth which has been adopted in Switzerland's constitution in 2003. First, using a synthetic control method I find that over the period 2003-2018, Switzerland had an average 0.95% higher growth compared to a counterfactual scenario without BBR. In addition, Switzerland's GDP has been higher than the counterfactual's during the entire post-intervention period (2003-2018). The difference reached 15% in 2013. Second, I make a growth accounting with a neoclassical growth model. I find that the increase in Switzerland's growth is due to the increase in TFP (which includes institutions) and not to changes in labor or capital accumulation. Third, I build an endogenous growth model with a government making inefficient decisions for political reasons. I find that by reducing public debt the BBR tempers the "crowding-out effect of debt" and frees up resources for private investment in R&D and by reducing the service of the debt frees up resources for public investment in R&D. These investments in turn foster economic growth through their effect on TFP. I also find that the BBR over the business cycle exhibits higher welfare gain compared to traditional BBRs that focus on deficits caps.

JEL Classification: E62, H63, O43, O47

some recommendations for trade and monetary policies.

Keywords: Balanced Budget Rule, Public debt, Economic growth

tries. WAEMU, having historically had its main trading partners outside Africa, will have to trade more within the continent. This paper identifies African countries with which WAEMU could increase its trade, and studies the implications of such an increase on macroeconomic stability, before proposing a monetary policy orientation to minimize the impact of external shocks. To do so, we develop a new approach to detect the trade expansion potential between two economies. This approach, applied to WAEMU countries using the Harmonized System's detailed four-digit product classification, over the period 1996 to 2016, reveals that South Africa, Egypt, Morocco, Nigeria, Tunisia, Kenya, and Ghana are the countries with the highest potential for trade expansion with WAEMU. With the AfCFTA, WAEMU could increase its imports by more than 12% on average with each of the African partners listed above. This figure reaches 32% for South Africa, the first potential partner. Using a new Keynesian model in an open economy, calibrated to WAEMU, we simulate several trade integration scenarios, targeted at the partners identified above. We find that greater integration with these countries will increase the transmission of price and production shocks from African partners to the WAEMU economy. The Cen-

tral Bank (BCEAO) within a framework of an optimal monetary policy should, in addition to inflation, react more to variations in the effective nominal exchange rate. Based on these results, the paper makes

WAEMU facing AfCFTA: implications for trade and monetary policies, with Régis Kouassi The purpose of the AfCFTA is to reduce trade barriers for greater integration between African coun-

JEL Classification: E43, E52, E58, F13, F15, F17, R13 Keywords: AfCFTA, WAEMU, BCEAO, free trade, monetary policy